

James Hodge

Doctoral Trainee at Open Lab, Newcastle, UK User Experience Researcher

Contact



j.hodge1@ncl.ac.uk



james_h0dge

PROFILE

PhD student at Open Lab, Newcastle University. My research focuses on creating positive experiences using Virtual Reality with people living with dementia, exploring the importance of using personal and non-personal designed VR environments which orients towards the present and makes use of a full spectrum of interactivity.

EXPERIENCE

2018 - PRESENT

Demonstrator & Supervisor | Newcastle University

Effectively managed the supervision of two undergraduate students, including dissertation feedback, assisting with planning and organising of workshop activities. I contributed to teaching in practicals of 60+ students by aiding in problemsolving their code and ideas for their final assessment.

2012 - PRESENT

Photographer | Freelance

Built authentic relationships with clients to gain their trust in capturing and editing photographs for weddings, conferences, and research workshops.

2016 - 2017

UX Designer | Freelance

Worked with clients to research, design, and prototype UX experiences for websites and apps, used Adobe CC and Sketch throughout the process.

2014 - 2016

Director of Photography | Oxygen Films

Managed and directed over 20 crew members on the set of full-feature films. Oversaw and collaborated with creative teams to curate a film that reflected the director's vision and style.

2013 - 2014

Office Assistant | Cogent Law

Demonstrated capacity to provide extensive support for seniorlevel staff, including managing day-to-day paperwork and maintaining electronic copies.

SKILLS

Experience-centered Design

Qualitative Research

Communicating Research

Virtual Reality

Unity

Javascript / HTML

Adobe CC

Sketch

Project management

Problem Solving

Decision-making

Analysis

Time Management

Adaptability

EDUCATION

2018 - PRESENT

PhD Computer Science | Newcastle University

The PhD centres around designing VR experiences with people living with dementia to support their wellbeing and quality of life. Working closely with the community, the introduction of VR technologies aims to evoke emotion, engage in creative, and support inclusion.

2017 - 2018

MRes Digital Civics (First Class) | Newcastle University

The dissertation focused on exploring personalising media experiences with the person living with dementia and their ecology of care that gained recognition at CHI'19. Through the master's course, I learned a more in-depth understanding of digital civics, ubiquitous technologies, and machine learning.

2014 - 2017

BSc Computer Science (First Class) | Newcastle University During my undergraduate degree, I learnt a diverse array of skills in computing science, including HCI, software design, web and app development. For my final dissertation, I explored the design of tailored VR experiences for people living with dementia. I presented this work at CHI'18 and earned honourable mention.

PUBLICATIONS

Intersections in HCI, Design and Dementia: Inclusivity in Participatory Approaches

R Brankaert, G Kenning, D Welsh, S Foley, J Hodge, D Unbehaun Companion Publication of the 2019 on DIS

Using Design Fiction to Explore the Ethics of VR 'In the Wild'

DP Green, GP Schofield, J Hodge, M Rose, K Cater, C Bevan, SI Gray Proceedings of the 2019 ACM International Conference on TVX

2019

Participatory Design of a Virtual Reality-Based Reentry Training with a Women's Prison

MQ Teng, J Hodge, E Gordon, Extended Abstracts of the 2019 CHI

Exploring Media Capture of Meaningful Experiences to Support Families Living with Dementia

J Hodge, K Montague, S Hastings, K Morrissey, Proceedings of the

2018



CHI'18 Mention

Exploring the design of tailored virtual reality experiences for people with dementia

J Hodge, M Balaam, S Hastings, K Morrissey Proceedings of the 2018 CHI

INTERESTS











Gardening Gaming